Hi everyone, welcome back.
In this lecture, we're gonna talk
about Texas data,
but I wanna be very
clear right at the start
about the framing.
So, text analysis is
not about a single method,
it's about a pipeline.
I'm insight into this
because many people encounter
text analysis for the first time
through a specific tool.
Maybe topic models,
sentiment analysis,
transformer models, and
they come away thinking
the model is the method.
In practice, the model's option is
the least important part.
The biggest threat to
validity usually happens
before the model ever sees the data,
when you decide
what text to include,
how to clean it, and
how to represent it.
These decisions
quietly shape your measure,
what your measure
actually is capturing.
So today, I'm gonna walk the
pipeline end-to-end,
collection,
cleaning, representation,
modeling, and validation.
In each step, I'll be
explicit about what assumptions
you're making and
what kinds of meaning
you're throwing away.
I want you to come
away from this lecture
thinking less like which
algorithm should I use,
and more like what
exactly am I measuring,
and how did I construct it.
So, why text data?
Text is one of the most common forms
of social data we have.
A huge amount of
political and social behavior
leads to textual traces,
things like news articles,
speeches, press
releases, social media posts,
policy documents, internal memos,
and court filings.
If you wanna study
ideology, prep framing,
blame attribution,
legitimacy claims,
agenda setting or persuasion,
text is often the
primary observable output.
So here's a simple example.
If you wanna study how governments
justify the use of force,
the justification is not
a number, it's a speech.
It's an oppressed
statement, it's the language,
the text is the outcome.
But text presents a challenge.
So unlike survey data or
administrative data,
text does not come
naturally in rows and columns.
There's no obvious
variable called front level
or ideological position.
So when we analyze text, we're not
just analyzing data,
we are constructing data.
That's the core message here.
Text is data, but only after we
build a measurement pipeline.
So this is the conceptual
background of the lecture.
Text analysis is a pipeline.
We have collection,
cleaning, representation,
modeling and validation.
Each tape shapes the inference.
So that's not a
metaphor, it's literal.
If you change what
documents collect,
you change the population of text.
If you change cleaning,
you change what
language counts as the same.
If you change representation,
you change what
similarity even means.
And if you change the model,
you change how
patterns are summarized.
So here's a real
example from practice.
Two researchers analyze the same set
of political speeches.
One removes all
procedural languages,
things like thank you,
honor to be here and so on.
The other keeps it.
They then run topic models.
One finds a strong national unity
topic, the other does not.
The difference within the model is
the cleaning step.
So as we go through the
pipeline and keep asking,
what is this step
doing to the meaning?
So raw text is not analysis ready.
Raw text contains
formatting, HTML markup,
boilerplate
language, navigation text,
disclaimers,
footnotes, repeat headers
and duplicated content.
And the key line to this slide
is one that you're
gonna internalize.
Preprocessing decisions are
theoretical decisions.
Preprocessing often feels boring.
It feels like janitorial work,
but it's actually where you decide
what counts as signal.
So let's make this concrete.
Suppose you're
studying stream and spreader,
can you move all religious
references at stop words?
You just remove core
ideological content.
Suppose you strip numbers because
numbers aren't words.
You might remove casualty counts
or dates that signal escalation.
Suppose you lowercase
everything in claps acronyms.
You might blur distinction between
institutions and concepts.
These aren't technical mistakes.
They're theoretical assumptions
about what language matters.
So preprocessing is
not a neutral step.
It's part of your
measurement instrument,
just like survey design.
So tokenization is where
text is broken to units.
These units might be
words, subwords or characters,
and the choice matters more than the
people often realize.
The pseudo code that I list here is
intentionally simple.
We're loading our documents here.
We're tokenizing the
data in this process here.
We're normalizing it,
we're removing stop words,
and we're storing the results.
But each of these
tests encodes assumptions.
So word tokenization assumes words
are the right unit of meaning.
That's intuitive, but it
breaks down with rare words,
spelling variation, or
multilingual corpora.
Subword tokenization, which is a
common in transformers,
allows models to handle unknown
words in morphology.
But it also makes
interpretation harder.
Because your units are no longer
meaningful in isolation,
character tokenization can handle
creative language and misspelling,
but it radically changes what
meaning even looks like.
So tokenization is not
just a technical step,
it's the first step where you define
the granularity of meaning.
That rewards the classic
pipeline representation.
You build a vocabulary,
count how often each term
appears in each
document and store the results.
The key conceptual
point here is that
Beggar words prioritize
transparency over semantics.
This is why Beggar
words are still widely used.
You can open the matrix and see
exactly what's being counted.
You can inspect coefficients
and trace them back to the words.
But it also ignores word order.
That means not good and
good can look similar.
Negation is hard for Beggar words.
Starchism will disappear.
Multivore
expressions get broken apart
unless you explicitly model them.
So Beggar words is often a
defensible starting point,
especially for exploratory work,
but it's important to be explicit
about what it cannot capture.
Turn frequency, inverse document
frequency weighting
is a refinement for Beggar words.
It downweights words
that appear everywhere
and upweights words
that are distinctive
to particular documents.
This is extremely useful for tasks
like document
similarity or clustering.
But TF-IDF encodes a value judgment.
Distinctive language matters more
than shared language.
It's often what you
want, but not always.
So if you're studying census farming
or shared ideology,
the most important
words might be the ones
that everyone uses,
but TF-IDF will push
those to the background.
So TF-IDF is not
better than Beggar words.
It's Beggar words with a different
theory or importance.
So I just wanna ground this in a
little bit of an anecdote
from a classic
political science research
that uses this process.
Someone was studying rhetoric
between Republicans,
Democrats, and their parties.
And when they were
trying to figure out
what words are very distinct,
an example of this for identifying
libertarian speeches
or documents with
the use of raw milk
as a discussion.
It's something that they only were,
until kind of recently actually,
they were the
primary political party
that was fighting for
things like raw milk.
So if you see a
constitutional document
that discusses something like that,
it's a highly
correlated or associated
with libertarian
political movements.
But things like the word liberty,
oh, I'm sorry,
liberty, authoritarian.
Things like words
like liberty, patriotism,
other words are actually shared
between all the political parties.
So TF-IDF does a nice job of
identifying words
that are very unique to a set of
certain documents.
Embeddings represent a more
fundamental shift.
Instead of counting words,
embeddings tax into
a geometric space.
So similar meanings
correspond to proximity.
So that's very powerful.
Synonyms can be close even if
they're different words
and context matters in this space.
But you lose a lot of transparency.
You're no longer
saying this word increased,
you're saying this document moved
closer to that document.
That means embeddings demand
stronger validation.
You need to show
that the geometry aligns
with your substantive concept,
not just the model as well.
So topic models are designed to
summarize large corpora.
They identify
patterns of co-occurrence
and label them as topics.
The most important
line in this slide is
topics summarize patterns, they're
not ground truth.
Topic models don't discover
the true ideological
structure of politics.
They reflect your
pre-processing, your vocabulary,
and your modeling choices.
So I've seen topic
models change dramatically
when a researcher slightly adjust
the document length
or remove a handful of
high-frequency words.
So topic models are useful,
especially for exploration,
but they require careful
interpretation of robustness checks.
So transformers are currently
dominant in many text tones.
But I want you to think of them as
pipelines, not magic boxes.
They tokenize text in
a model specific way,
encode contextual representations,
pull those representations, and then
optionally fine tune them.
They model context explicitly, which
is a major advantage,
but they also
magnify upstream decisions.
Over selection, pre-processing,
and labeling matter even more,
because the representations are
harder to inspect.
High performance does not excuse
weak measurement states.
Here's just some coding.
We have our tokenizer, our
transformer here,
pulling our hidden state, and then
some fine tuning processes.
This is what a Python setup would
look like for this.
So this is where many
text-to-data projects fail.
Text models can fail silently.
They can produce
outputs that look clean,
quantitative, and convincing, while
being driven by artifice.
So we have to validate.
These two habits
matter enormously for them.
So the first is
running sensitivity checks.
You want to run your pipeline and
your alternative
pre-processing choices
and see what changes.
And then the second
is stability checks.
You want to rerun models with
different random seeds.
If your results depend
heavily on one choice,
it's not necessarily fatal,
but it changes how
strong your claim should be.
So validation is
optional is part of the method.
So validation is not optional is
part of your method.
So bias enters text
pipelines everywhere.
Corporate selection reflects
platform incentives,
institutional
constraints, and visibility.
Pre-processing decisions reflect
your theory of meaning.
Pre-chain models inherit biases from
the training data,
labeling imports human judgment.
But here's the key takeaway.
Upstream choices
dominate downstream results.
If you remember what
incentives to manufacture,
this is the really important one.
So every text pipeline should
document where the corpus came from,
how it was cleaned.
These are
pre-processing steps, typically.
How it's represented as
bag of words embedding TFIDF.
What models are used and what are
their parameters,
and how the results were validated.
This is what makes
text analysis auditable.
So if someone cannot reconstruct
your text and how
it was transformed,
they cannot evaluate measures.
Audible pipelines are
reproducible pipelines.
So what we emphasize in practice,
let me summarize what we need.
We want to do
pipelines over a single model,
simplicity before complexity,
validation over accuracy,
and transparency in pre-processing.
So these principles are once
separate rigorous text-as-data work
from black box number generation.
So let me close with a few
questions to keep in mind.
Where does the meaning get lost in
your text pipelines?
So when you're going from a very
complex text corpus to bag of words,
you're losing a lot of information.
When you are removing stop words,
you might be losing
a lot of information,
changing punctuation
of removing numbers.
These are all common
pre-processing steps,
but they can fundamentally change
the data that we're looking at.
And that's just
looking at bag of words.
Things like embedding spaces or
context-forward embedding spaces
also have a ton of meaning,
but that can be affected by the
pre-training process
before you get into it.
So think about what text
is lost and what names lost.
Then you want to think about which
decisions matter most
for your research questions.
So does removing numbers help or
hurt your ability to understand
the text that you're analyzing?
And you can do that for any type of
pre-processing step.
And then how should
uncertainty be communicated
when text-driven measures are
sensitive to pre-processing on it?
So we're going to explore more of
this in the lab today.